<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologie of infants in a sermon: prouing, by the reuealed will of God, that children preuented by death of their baptisme, by Gods election, may be saued. By W.H. preacher in the Tower of London. Seene and allowed  by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Hubbock, William, b. 1560.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840006</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1384:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologie of infants in a sermon: prouing, by the reuealed will of God, that children preuented by death of their baptisme, by Gods election, may be saued. By W.H. preacher in the Tower of London. Seene and allowed  by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Hubbock, William, b. 1560.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 61, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the widowe Orwin for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Hubbocke.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon touching the vnbaptized.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:1"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGIE OF INFANTS IN A SERMON: Prouing, by the reueal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will of God, that children preuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by death of their Baptiſme, by Gods elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W. H. <hi>Preacher in the Tower of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seene and allowed by Authoritie.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>BY WISDOME PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY</head>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by the Widowe <hi>Orwin</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD ROBERT <hi>DEVOROX,</hi> EARLE of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and one of her Maieſties moſt <hi>Honorable priuie Councel: all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> fit for ſo worthie place and truſt be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great Meſsias, the Lord Ieſus (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) being on the Croſſe readie to dye, caſt his eye aſide, and ſawe his mother and the diſciple ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by, whom hee loued, on whoſe breaſt he leaned: and ſayd to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Woman behold thy ſonne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 19.26.</note> and to the diſciple, <hi>Behold thy mother.</hi> This voyce then ſpake from the altar of the croſſe on earth: The ſame voyce ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſpeake ſtill from the arch of heauen, the Church being grauen on
<pb facs="tcp:4474:3"/>
the palme of his hands,<note place="margin">Eſay. 49.16.</note> and her walles euer in his ſight on the one ſide, &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nobles of the world on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide, eſpecially ſuch Nobles who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee loueth, on whoſe ſhoulders his truth leaneth, in whoſe breaſt the loue of the trueth dwelleth: He ſeemeth to ſay to the Church, as to a faint &amp; weak woman of them: O woman behold thy ſonnes the Nobles of the earth: Pſal. 45.16. Thou ſhalt haue children the Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates thorow the whole earth. And to them: O ye ſonnes of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,<note place="margin">Galath. 4.26.</note> behold your mother alſo. This mother, the true Church, maketh you the ſonnes of God. That voyce then wrought obedience: he to whom it was ſpoken, tooke it to heart, and took her home: So ought the Peeres and States of the world, eſpecially whom Ieſus hath loued by education in the trueth, to take this mother the church, her ſonnes and daughters, the trueth and her defence home to them, to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round it with their power and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, euen as in two circles Iſrael
<pb facs="tcp:4474:3"/>
with all their tribes and gouernours did hemme in the Tabernacle of God, Numb. 3.38. In the inmoſt circle <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> on the forefront of the Tabernacle Eaſtward ſtood next to it: verſ 24. On the other ſide three fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Leui:</hi> The Gerſonites pitched their tents behinde the Tabernacle Weſtward: verſ 29. The Kohathites had their ſtanding on the South ſide: verſ. 35. The Merarites on the North ſide. Theſe were the inward liſts of it. In the outward wall of it (ſo to ſpeak) Eaſtward did <hi>Iuda</hi> claſpe it in, and his aſſociates <hi>Iſſachar</hi> and <hi>Zabulon:</hi> Num. 2.5. On the South ſide, verſ. 10. <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ben</hi> faſtned his ſtandard with <hi>Gad</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon:</hi> On the Weſt, verſ. 18. ioyned <hi>Ephraim</hi> with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min:</hi> On the North, verſ. 24. as cloſing vp all, came <hi>Dan</hi> with <hi>Aſher</hi> and <hi>Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali.</hi> So ſtrongly and politically was Gods Tabernacle and Church then mannaged and conducted: in ſo ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner did it march on with this alarme: Num. 10.35. <hi>Ariſe O Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:4474:4"/>
and let thine enemies be ſcatrered.</hi> In ſo puiſſant and ſtable manner did it take vp his ſtanding with this ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: <hi>Returne O Lorde to the many thouſands of Iſrael.</hi> The Nobles who thus ſtand about Gods Church at this time, and lend their ſhoulders for his trueth to leane vpon, haue a greater place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Naamans:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.18.</note> the King to leane on their hands: then <hi>Atlas,</hi> the arch of heauen to reſt vpon their ſhoulders: they haue the honour to be the noble diſciples who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus loueth, on whoſe breaſts he leaneth, in whoſe hearts he dwelleth: to whom he hauing ſayd, Behold your mother, the Church, the trueth: they doe not onely take her home to them vnder their roofe, dwel with it, conuerſe with it: but enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrict vow and ſolemne proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (for this is the heroicall prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant) as <hi>Ruth</hi> the Moabitiſh did to <hi>Naomi:</hi> concerning her cleauing to the trueth and Gods people, though diſcouraged by contrarie example of one that lay in the ſame wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, though
<pb facs="tcp:4474:4"/>
aboured with by the womb that bare her: ſhe ſayd,<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Intreate me not to leaue thee, nor to depart from thee: whither thou goeſt, I will goe: where thou dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, I will dwell: thy people ſhall be my people: thy God, my God: where thou dyeſt, I will dye: and there will I be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. The Lord doe ſo vnto me, and more alſo if ought but death part thee and me.</hi> The obedience to this voyce of God, to take the loue of the trueth home to you, ſeeing it hath dwelt in your familie and progenie long, and now hereditarily reſteth in your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: and the experience of your care, by whoſe meanes not onely the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the preaching of the word is lift vp in this place, <hi>(tanquam in arce Minerua Phidiae)</hi> in the midſt of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiued enemies (which was not before) but by whoſe fruites of faith alſo it is cheriſhed: emboldened me to preſent this firſtling of my labors in this kind, in the cauſe of many ſpeechles infants, to your Honour: remembring what <hi>Salomons</hi> mother ſayd to him: <hi>Open
<pb facs="tcp:4474:5"/>
thy mouth for the dumme in the cauſe of all the children of destruction Open thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pouer. 31.8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The argument, though diminutiue and low, yet parents loue to heare of the ſtate of their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life: much more of life to come, ſpecially the godly. Euen graue fathers after ſerious matters diſpatched, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare not to vſe modificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpeech, to liſpe with the little ones: ſaying, <hi>Cheſippus,</hi> not <hi>Chryſippus:</hi> as he in <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: Coniah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 22.</note> not <hi>Ieconiah:</hi> as in the ſcripture. But why do I ſeeke further? Haue not theſe little ones the Dukes and Pecres of heauen for their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones?<note place="margin">Matth. 18.10.</note> Their Angels (ſayth Chriſt) alwaies behold the face of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen. And he that ſet a child in the midſt of his Apoſtles, ſtriuing for honour,<note place="margin">Matth. 18.3</note> with this charge: Verely, except ye be conuerted and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen: and he that humbleth himſelfe as this child, is the greateſt in the kingdome of heauen: knew that the caſe of little children,
<pb facs="tcp:4474:5"/>
their harmleſnes, innocencie, mildnes, are matters for all ſorts to meditate vpon, to ſchoole them to GOD. In which argument <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo profited, Pſalm. 131.2. that he profeſſeth euen before the Lorde, that he demeaned himſelf as a weaned, euen as a weaned child, though the court and field had been his nurſe. But I may not exceede the meaſure of a Preface: The Lord ripen the good worke he hath begun in your Honour, and increaſe it with the mightie increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors in the Lord to be commanded:</hi> William Hubbocke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the bleſſing of peace is great, <hi>Zach. 8.8.</hi> ſtreets full of children playing, ſo among them to come ſodainely the ſtroke of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.29.</note> as at midnight in Aegypt,<note place="margin">Virgil. Aeneid. lib 4. Si quis mihi paruulus aula Luderet AEneas. Act. 20.9. 1. King. 17.18. Ionas 4.7. 2 Sam. 12.17.</note> in euery houſe a dead childe, to fall dead from a windowe as <hi>Eutichus,</hi> to ſicken in the field, and die at home preſently, as the woman of <hi>Sareptaes</hi> childe: especially if it enioy not the next morning ſunne, as <hi>Ionas</hi> ſhade, especially if it dye as <hi>Dauids</hi> child did before circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo it before baptiſme: &amp; the former ioy doubleth the grief, ſillie leauened people lift vp their voice as <hi>Agar</hi> did for hers,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.19.</note> in a gentiles diſtrust as a people without hope,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.13.</note> (as though their babe were <hi>Iſmael</hi> &amp; of Aegypt, &amp; not of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell of God: as though they were <hi>Agar</hi> of Sina engendring vnto bondage, &amp; not of Sion, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto God) moning there is no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: they blame not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that they keep not
<pb facs="tcp:4474:7"/>
houres with God and his Church, in regarde of goſſips and outward complement, breaking out as the Sareptane:<note place="margin">1. King. 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>O thou man of God, what haue I to doe with thee?</hi> Would to God they would thinke alſo with that good woman: God in my childe brings my ſinnes to remembrance, that departure of children might cauſe departure from iniquitie. For many take on piteouſly with God and man if their children miſſe Baptiſme: but take no care if they miſcarie their owne Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> forgetting the fellowſhip of the bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, into which they were baptized: ſo that the water of Baptiſme is not the ſweet water of life vnto life,<note place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> but Marah, as in <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus:</hi> A gall of bitternes ſtill in him. Christ ſhould diſſolue the workes of the diuell,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.8.</note> but a bond of iniquitie in him ſtill. To ſuch it ſhould bee fearefull in their eares which is written: <hi>The children which yee ſayd ſhould bee a praye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1.19</note> 
               <hi>and your ſonnes &amp; daughters, which haue no knowledge between good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, they ſhall poſſeſſe mine inheritance:</hi> but as for you, <hi>Numb. 14.32.</hi> Your carkeiſes ſhall fall in the deſart. Where is he that hath <hi>Dauids</hi> hart, a man after Gods owne hart? he moned for feare of death,<note place="margin">2. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but neuer moued to haue reſpite of life for circumciſion, which no
<pb facs="tcp:4474:7"/>
doubt he would if it had beene ſo daungerous to haue dyed without it: at least where is the mouth of <hi>Iob?</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord that gaue mee children: bleſſed bee the Lord that tooke away my children: bleſſed is he in giuing, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in taking away, and bleſſed in the manner though ſtrange: of him it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſinned not with his mouth, nor charged God foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly.</hi> But thy child is thine Image, and thy ſhadow: and behold as <hi>Ionas</hi> ſhade, it vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thee in a night, it vaniſhed before thou well lookedſt vpon the face of it: &amp; howe pitifull a thing?<note place="margin">Ionas 4 11.</note> But the pitifull God telleth him and thee alſo: that hee pitieth little ones that cannot diſcerne betweene right hands and left, euen to the number of ſix ſcore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in one citie: and that in Aſhur, and Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niueh; and is his compaſſion ſhut vp from the ſeede of Christians? Yea but if it had beene ſprinkled with water of Baptiſme, <hi>Iohn 5.7.</hi> When the bedridden man for <hi>38.</hi> yeares had none to helpe him into the ſouereigne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Christ healed him without water ſaying, verſ. <hi>17.</hi> Though the Angell moue not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the water, verſ. <hi>4.</hi> but at times, yet ſaith he, My Father ſtill worketh and I alſo work. And though the ſpring of Baptiſme ſhould ſometime be dammed vp: it followeth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb facs="tcp:4474:8"/>
to bee damned: for as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>Ioh. 4.32. I haue meate that you know not of:</hi> ſo the Angell telleth <hi>Agar,</hi> and all mothers of water that ſhe ſeeth not: and Chriſt here telleth of ſaluation, which the Angell and the water wrought not. Thou miſſeſt thy children in thine armes: beholde they are in the hand of God, they are pluckt from thy breſts, but are in Abrahams boſome: not in thy cradle below, but in the throne of immortalitie aboue. How oft is it ſeene amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men that friendes take a babe from a weake mother, a daughter, a nurſe, and bring it vp for their owne:<note place="margin">Exod. 2.10.</note> as <hi>Pharaos</hi> daughter did <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo that the parents peraduenture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee it: or not till long after. What elſe doth God when he taketh the childe from the wombe, or breaſt, to haue it nurſed in heauen loſt it ſhould haue ill bringing vp here? A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with ſuch diſpoſitions vpon a like ſodaine accident, made mee gather against the next Lords day, theſe remembrances touching this argument, which nowe I haue more perfectly recognized. Then it bred ſuch alteration in their apprehenſions and opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that heard it: that as once they who ſayd of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.4.</note> hee was a murderer, (as if ſome ſhould ſay, <hi>infancieida,</hi>) when they ſawe the reuealed glorie of God:
<pb facs="tcp:4474:8"/>
they changed their mindes. Theſe alſo are a holy ſeede, <hi>Luk. 15.31.</hi> The childe that was dead to mee, is aliue: he that was loſt is found: blaming themſelues as <hi>Dauid, Pſal. 73.23.</hi> ſo fooliſh were wee euen as beaſtes, vntill wee we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctuary of God, where we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the end eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe little ones.<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> The Lord of the harueſt giue bleſſing to this, according to the riches of his glorious wiſedome, and teach vs to abound not with captious know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which by ſcanninges, deſcantings, comparings puffeth vp, <hi>1. Cor 8.1.</hi> But to abounde with loue which buildeth vs vp to one heade ouer all, euen the Lord Jeſus, to whom be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed ſaluation for euer.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4474:9"/>
            <head>A SERMON PROOVING, THAT THE VNBAPTIZED, PREVENTED BY DEATH, may be Gods children: and by his election may be ſaued.</head>
            <head type="sub">THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Pet. 3.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>To this Arke of Noah, the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure alſo that now ſaueth vs, euen Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme agreeth, not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh, but the questioning of a good conſcience to God, by the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Christ.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Who is at the right hand of God, gone into Heauen, to whome the Angels and powers, and principalities are ſubiect.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture, as touching my purpoſe at this time, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the meanes of our ſaluation, and that two waies, touching GOD in Chriſt, &amp; touching vs. Touching god in Chriſt: who is the cauſe of it, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4474:10"/>
and ſoueraigne cauſe of it, the cauſe of cauſes, euen Chriſt the alone cauſe of our ſaluation. The meanes of performing and purchaſing it, are ſet downe by foure actions: the firſt, his riſing from the dead: the ſecond, his ſitting at the right hand of God: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his aſcending into heauen: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his ſubiecting of Angels vnto him. The conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on our part is two-fold: outward, the element of water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: inwarde, the queſtioning of a good conſcience to God. Of the type <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke and the complement of it, in the correſpondence of Baptiſme vnto it: elſewhere hath been at large handled.</p>
            <p>Now further, I obſerue affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, what ſaueth: Namely, Chriſt apprehended by faith, from a good conſcience: as being riſen, aſcended, ſitting at Gods right hand, ſubduing Angels and all for thy good. Secondly, I obſerue negatiuely what ſaueth not: namely, the outward waſhing of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: water of it ſelfe, being readier
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4474:10"/>
to drowne, then to ſaue: ſeeing of old they baptized with their bodies vnder the water, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16. and not ſprinkled alone, which yet was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, as appeareth <hi>Act.</hi> 9.17.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Cyp. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 7. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is neceſſarie and fit to bee had, if it may bee had after Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. So that the Prince, Miniſter, or parent, or whoſoeuer he bee, ſore offendeth, by whoſe negligence, or meanes it is omitted, or cannot be had. For the firſt, all ſcripture aimeth onely at this poynt, Ieſus to be the Chriſt: all the ſacrifices of the old Teſtament did foreſignifie it: <hi>Iohn</hi> did poynt at him, <hi>This lambe takes away the ſinnes of the worlde:</hi> GOD proclaimed it from heauen by an apparition of a Doue, with a celeſtiall oracle, when he was crowned with the holie Ghoſt: <hi>This is my welbeloued ſinne in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> I am not pleaſed in the Prophets, in any holie men or women, not in thee, nor in thy people,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4474:11"/>
O my ſeruant <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> nor in this water of Iorden, but in him I am well pleaſed, euen for all other that beleeue in his name:<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.1.2</note> of him (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>If any ſinne we haue an aduocate with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he is the propitiation for our ſinnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> There is no ſaluation in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no name vnder heauen, by which we may be ſaued: no name neither of perſon, as Angels or Saints: nor yet of other creature, as Water, Bread, or Wine.</p>
            <p>This I neede not to ſtande vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians: the meanes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to vs muſt bee thought vpon rather, which is by faith vnfained, which maketh the queſtioning of a good conſcience towards God: here a good conſcience well examined is mentioned. But to <hi>Timothie</hi> and to the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> it is thus expreſſed: vnto <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> thus:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note>* <hi>The end of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is loue out of a pure hart, from a good conſcience, and faith vnfained.</hi> Againe to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> thus:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> * <hi>Let vs draw neere with a true heart in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4474:11"/>
of faith, ſprinkled in our hearts from an euill conſcience.</hi> Then what ſanctifieth the conſcience? faith. Now a good conſcience is here deſcribed, to bee ſuch an one that maketh ſuch an enquirie into it ſelfe, by ſtraight exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, as in Gods preſence: exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a good conſcience to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, tho men miſlike: So that that is not an ill conſcience that ſinneth: for then who is free? but that which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth ſinne to lie vpon it ſelfe vnexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, that flattereth it ſelfe, that bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtereth ſinne in it ſelfe and others. <hi>Paul</hi> would bee one among them that ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Steuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.58. Act. 22.20.</note> at leaſt he would keepe their garments: if it ſhould come to voyces, he would giue a voyce,<note place="margin">Act. 9.1.2.3.</note> yea he put himſelfe to paine to moleſt men &amp; women that loued the trueth,<note place="margin">Act. 23.1. Act. 24.16.</note> and yet when he had beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt, he profeſſed before the Councell, that he had ſerued GOD in a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Therefore that is not an euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, alwaies that hath been defiled,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4474:12"/>
but that which lyes in the defilement. For if thou riſeſt from ſinne, this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſitting at the right hand of God, this aſcenſion, this ſubduing of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly powers, are for ſeruiceablenes vnto thee: they bee as a bunch tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to beſprinkle thine heart. Thou art cleane: euen as <hi>Dauid</hi> profeſſeth of himſelfe, after he had been bathed in pleaſure, and been dyed red as ſcarlet in the bloud of <hi>Vrias,</hi> that if God waſh him,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51.7.</note> bloud it ſelfe, and adulterie ſhall bee as cleane waſht off, as though they had neuer been. A man ſo ſcoured ſhal be as white as ſnowe in his cleanenes from the clowdes: a man ſo ſpotted ſhall bee as cleare as the picked, the ſmooth and cleare tranſparent glaſſe, when the ſunne beames do ſhine vpon it. Yea but ſome wil ſay: though with God it bee ſo, that my ſinnes bee taken away,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51.3.</note> yet my ſinne is alwaies before me, it runnes in my mind, I can haue no reſt for it. Yet againe remember, as the ſcripture ſayth,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.20.</note> Though thy heart condemne thee, yet this Chriſt ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4474:12"/>
ſo aſcending, ſo ſitting in glorie, that Angels that do homage vnto him, euen as he is man: is greater then thy condemning heart to ſaue thee. And therefore beloued, to the man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom ſinne or ſathan hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, his owne fleſh, or the world, I ſay, let not ſinne lye vnexamined, vnque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned with neuer examining the hart and raines: but rather ſtill as ſinne ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon thee, ſearch it out, as with tents wee ſearch the bottome of our ſores, lance the wound,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.31.</note> ſit in commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon thy ſelfe, caſt thy ſelfe, and damne thy ſelfe, and thou ſhalt bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: if thou doeſt thus, thou haſt the right vſe of Baptiſme, of the Supper, of the Word, of Prayer, and all the good that can come to a man by Chriſtes death, reſurrection, aſcenſion, ſitting in glorie, and power ouer Angels: thou ſhalt ſtop the mouth of Sathan: <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.10. <hi>He is an accuſer of the brethren.</hi> Doe thou therfore ſtep to God before him: when ſathan ſeeth, that thou haſt done ſo much againſt thy ſelfe, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4474:13"/>
thy ſelfe, as he deſired to doe, he will depart confounded. Laſtly, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that a man that beareth with his own ſoule in ſinne, or with others, that winketh at it, that lends the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of letter, cloth, good, word, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, colours, ſhifts, that neuer calleth himſelfe to queſtion, whether he ſtand in ſtate of grace, in what caſe hee is with God, being froſen in his dregges: this man hath no part with Ieſus in the holie citie, his Baptiſme waſheth him not, his bodie ſprinkled towards men, but not his conſcience to God: Chriſt roſe from death, he lyes ſtill in ſinne: Chriſt ſits at Gods right hand, he ſits vpon the ſeate of wickedneſſe: Chriſt aſcended, &amp; he deſcendeth downward to hell: Chriſt hath Angels vnder him, he diuels aboue him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 2 part.</note>Now by the way of paſſage of ſpeech, to the next part, euen out of this place, I reaſon thus: He that ſaueth vs, muſt haue riſen from death, aſcended into heauen, ſit at Gods right hande, Angels alſo to adore him: but no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4474:13"/>
nor holie man, or woman euer did riſe for vs, or aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for vs: Baptiſme hath no ſuch power to raiſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, nor hath it ſelfe mounted to heauen, nor hath any place at Gods right hand, nor do the Angels worſhip it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of neceſsitie depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpon Baptiſme, though it ſhould bee moſt holilie miniſtred. The Popiſh Church hath two errors in it: the one,<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. cenſur. Colon. in dial. 7. de Sac.</note> that ſacraments by the work wrought by the receiuing of them, bring grace to the receiuer, vnles ſome enormous ſinne be vpon him, which they tearme mortall. Another, that children, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, innocents, if they dye without Baptiſme, they are damned.</p>
            <p>O cruell ſentence, and bloudie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. The firſt is refuted by that wee haue ſayd alreadie, that in them that haue yeares, no grace commeth by the ſacrament, but a diſgrace rather, no good but euill, if there bee not a good conſcience towards GOD examined, and waſhed with the fruites of Chriſts death and paſsion. For here are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4474:14"/>
the workes of his humiliation, as his incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dwelling in the ſhape of a ſeruant, his crucifying, and ſuch like, though there are touched onely foure workes of his exaltation. And our Apoſtle ſayth plainly, though <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> Arke ſaued, yet ſaying that the waſhing of the fleſh ſaueth not, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſay, gather not that outward waſhing ſaueth. How then ſay our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, that all are damned that haue not Baptiſme?<note place="margin">Teſt. Rhemiſ. Ioh. 3. verſ. 5.</note> or doe they ſay ſo? No not all, ſay they. Who then? and who not? All infants (ſay they) that dye without Baptiſme. O pitifull &amp; cruell ſentence, whoſe eares will not tingle at it? infants who cannot ſpeak, think, or do ill, the child whoſe fleſh is ſcarce curded in the wombe: whoſe bones are ſcarce griſtled out of the wombe: from the darknes of the wombe paſſe to the vtter darkneſſe for euer. Thus ſpeaketh the dragon all gored with bloud.<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But doth the lambe of God ſay ſo alſo? no doubt this lambes bloud ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4474:14"/>
it ſelf euen to theſe little la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes and ſucklings. Is there no pardon from this general da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natorie ſentence &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell definitiue? are none excepted? Yes, God doth accept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as baptized, who are martyred before they could be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,<note place="margin">Rhe. in Ioh. 5. verſ. 2.</note> and they that depart this life with deſire and vow of Baptiſme. Onely they? Yea onely they, who earneſtly intend, deſire and ſeeke for the ſame: that is a fewe, very fewe O happie &amp; rare caſe, of them aboue all others to be ſingled out vnto life. What is their proofe that the vnbaptized muſt needs be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned? <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>Vnles a man be borne of water and the holy Ghoſt:</hi> This is generall, euen againſt all whoſoeuer haue not outward water: and if gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, why not to martyrs and the other that dye with deſire of Baptiſme? But they can make general whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they will,<note place="margin">Pighius Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. eccl. l. 1. c. 4.</note> and ſpeciall when they will: euen as blaſphemouſly they haue ſayd of the Word, it is a noſe of waxe:<note place="margin">Linda. in praef.</note> ſo they make the ſacrament a ſcale of waxe. But ſuppoſe a Martyr, or a Chriſtian
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4474:15"/>
conuerted, not yet inſtructed in the doctrine of Baptiſme, as they that led the Martyrs to death, ſeeing their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, faith, zeale, were ſuddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, and cried out, <hi>Christianus ſum,</hi> I am a Chriſtian, and thereupon ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with them: how could they deſire that, they knowe not of? were they damned? for this Popiſh diuinitie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all damned, who in their owne perſons doe not earneſtly intend, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ſeeke for Baptiſme of water, euen as earneſtly as the proportion of the ſpeech carrieth it: as the man deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee in the water,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.6.7.</note> when it was troubled, and had none to helpe him. What then became of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> for who baptized him? He indeede ſayd to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 3 14.</note> 
               <hi>I haue neede to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of thee, and commeſt thou to me?</hi> He deſired it: but that is not enough, ſeeing hee liued in a time when hee might haue had it:<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.22. &amp; 4.2.</note> for Chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples then baptized. Or what ſhall wee ſay of the Apoſtles, who ſeeme (<hi>Act.</hi> 1.5.) to be borne indeede of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4474:15"/>
ſpirit, but not of the outward water, except <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Andrewe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.36.40.</note> and ſome that were <hi>Iohns</hi> diſciples, to haue been baptized with the holie Ghoſt, but not with water? What dare they ſay of the theefe, who was neither Martyr,<note place="margin">Acts 9.18.</note> nor yet was ſo farre inſtructed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire baptiſme of water, but by ſpeciall influence of Gods ſudden touch of his heart, and lightening of his minde,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.42.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to bee with Chriſt in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and obtained that princely para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe? Laſt of all, ſeeing themſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the deſire of parents, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers,<note place="margin">Catech. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</note> as they tearme them, ſerueth for to procure grace to children bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, who haue not the wit nor grace yet to aske it: why ſhould not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of parents, or friends, who hunger and thirſt for the righteouſnes of God in Baptiſme, for the infants to bee borne, or alreadie borne, and yet dying without baptiſme, be accepted in Gods ſight? Themſelues, for the innocents, and Martyrs whom <hi>Herod</hi> tragicallie murdered in the maſſacre of Bethlem,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4474:16"/>
and yet they not baptized, nor bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme deſired for them, leaſt of all this baptiſme of blood, which al lamented, al fathers and mothers cryed out vpon: themſelues I ſay confeſſe theſe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaued,<note place="margin">Rhe Teſt. in Math. 2.16.</note> but gloriouſly ſaued, to bee Martyrs, and ſolemnize their feaſt.</p>
            <p>And thus the ground and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is weake: their building alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, pau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheth. In the primitiue church of the world, no doubt many children dyed before the eight day vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as <hi>Dauids</hi> childe begotten in adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.18.</note> which dyed euen the ſeuenth day: the greater griefe, if it bee as they would haue it in baptiſme, that it came ſo neere the iuſt time, and miſſed the ſeale of the couenant: as it were a man eſcaping all ſhipwracke to die in the port &amp; hauen. Likewiſe the Iſraelites remained vncircumciſed without all deſire to haue it, counting it a rebuke, becauſe they learned heatheniſhnes of Aegypt,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 5.8.</note> or kept themſelues vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, as meaning to returne into Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Num. 14.4. Yet who dare be ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4474:16"/>
peremptorie,<note place="margin">Baptiſme the great Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, ſo called by Epiphanius</note> as to pronounce damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon them? for looke howe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme anſwereth circumciſion, ſo the deceaſing without baptiſme ſhould be by ſuite and proportion, no worſe thing then dying without circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Vnles a man will ſay, that the ſtate of the Goſpell hath leſſe mercy and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie then the lawe, and that it went har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with infants vnder Chriſt, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants vnder <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſeeing Chriſt alſo became an infant, to ſaue and redeeme infants: ſeeing alſo on them by <hi>Herod</hi> was laide the firſt teſtimonie, that the world ſhould hate the Lord Ieſus, euen yet, as it were a babe and ſuckling,<note place="margin">Math. 3.16.</note> and that vnto death. Adde hereunto that ſeeing the Lorde appointed a ſet time to circumciſion,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.12.</note> which was hard and dangerous, ſomwhat for life, <note n="*" place="margin">Ge. 34.25. in the Sichemites who were ſoare for the cutting three daies and not able to defend themſelues.</note> I meane the eight day, and deſigned no certaine time to baptize, that ſeeing it is freer for diſpoſing of, that leaſt of all necesſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dependeth vpon it: whereas if the 2 or 3. <note n="*" place="margin">As ſome in Cyp. time. l. 3. cp. 8. ep.</note> the 7. or 8. day had beene ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or ſuch like, then the defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4474:17"/>
of baptiſme beyond that time, had beene great offence: but the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the childe before that time no diſparagement to ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lombard l. 4. ſent. diſt. 2. ca. ſi vero.</note>Indeed <hi>Lombard</hi> the maiſter of the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that is of the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue diuinitie, (out of whom they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their tenents &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions) giueth da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natory ſentence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infants that die without circumciſion, as vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dye without baptiſme. But here he is noted with a blacke coa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of diſlike. None commonly holde with maſter <hi>Lombard</hi> in this:<note place="margin">Magiſter hic non tenetur.</note> onely our countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Beda</hi> thinking that verie hard, doth labour to ſalue &amp; qualifie it thus: that in time of necesſitie of death, they circumciſed peraduenture before the 8. day without offence. But who dare pluck vp the ſtakes of the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God,<note place="margin">Quaeſt. 3, de Baptiſmo.</note> or remoue them? It is but a fancie. The Ieſuites in their contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, yeeld the infants of the Iewes that were preuented by death before the 8. day, to bee ſaued: becauſe they ſay, God ſet downe this time. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4474:17"/>
the libertie that it is arbitrary to the church, when to adminiſter baptiſme, ſo no neglect bee of that holy ſeale, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth rather, that the preuention of it ſhould bee no more preiudiciall to the ſauing of thy child vnbaptized, then of it vncircumciſed. And the other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which the Ieſuits giue, why Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh infants might bee ſaued without circumciſion: namely, that the parents prayers and offeringes might bee a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to ſuccour them, will ſerue for the infants vnbaptized, if they meane of prayers before death: namely, that the deuotion of the godly, of godly parents, who many times pray, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe deuotion in their hearts for their babe vnſeene, (as <hi>Iob</hi> for his aliue,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.5. Gen. 25.22.</note> as <hi>Rebecca</hi> went to the Lorde for the babes in the wombe) that it may haue life, the mother a good howre: that it may proue the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God: ſhal be as auailable for their children, as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringes of the Iewes for their vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. But ſee the force of trueth, howe great it is, that it maketh ſtiffe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4474:18"/>
aduerſaries to yeeld ſomewhat, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that by priuiledge and diſpenſation infants vnbaptized may bee ſaued, for ſo at laſt they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.6.</note>But wee proue more then a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all priuiledge: <hi>Abraham</hi> before the lawe was iuſtified by faith:<note place="margin">Rom. 4 3.</note> euen while hee was yet vncircumciſed. <hi>Iohn</hi> the baptiſt,<note place="margin">Luke 1.15. Iere. 1.5.</note> in the wombe was filled with the holy Ghoſt: <hi>Ieremie</hi> vncircumciſed was ſanctified from his mothers wombe: ſo <hi>Paul</hi> vnbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed was ſanctified alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the womb:<note place="margin">Gal. 1.15.</note> if <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> had dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out circumciſion, had they been dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? if <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the wombe, had they periſhed? God forbid: where then is abſolute neceſsitie? Therefore indeede ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dependeth vpon Gods election of olde,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.5. Rom. 9.21.22.</note> when in his euerlaſting counſell, ſeeing a ruine like to come vpon all, he ſorted the ſoules of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſome to mercie, ſome to wrath: and this election remaineth ſure and vnmoueable in his church hauing this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4474:18"/>
ſeale, not that man knoweth by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or not baptiſme,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19,</note> who are his abſolutely: but * this the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his: ſo that indeede the holding of the neceſsitie of baptiſme to ſaluation ouerthroweth Gods ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, deſtroyeth his omnipotencie, and the freenes of his purpoſe from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. Of <hi>Iacob</hi> God ſayth, <hi>Him I haue loued:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.13.</note> in him is vnderſtood the corps of the faithfull, the communaltie of the ſaintes.</p>
            <p>Gods loue is no fancie that want of baptiſme may breake off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for then it were a heauie caſe, that the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or contempt of the parent or miniſter ſhould debarre the helpeles child from the ſocietie of ſaluation. <hi>Eſau</hi> hated of God: in him is vnderſtood the brood and ſpawne of the wicked: therefore ſaluation dependeth vpon Gods accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and receiuing into fauour, and not vpon the outwarde elemente of water, euen ritually and formally ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred: for to ſay that water hath this power, it is to deifie it, to make it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4474:19"/>
God, to make it an Idoll, to ſacrifice to it, and to bring vp again a <hi>Neptune,</hi> a God of the water with the gentiles.</p>
            <p>Therfore neither had <hi>Iacob</hi> periſhed if hee had died in the wombe, ſeeing GOD ſpred his banner of loue ouer him: neither <hi>Eſau</hi> was ſaued, becauſe hee liued till his foreskin was done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſeeing the Lord had no liking to him. The ſcripture is rich in exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods fauour before any touch of Sacraments, beſides theſe alreadie touched, the children of the Hebrues, (alſo as it is charitable and probable to thinke, <hi>Dauids</hi> childe,) <hi>Abraham, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Ieremie, Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Paul,</hi> the theefe vpon the croſſe, whom all the ſcripture commendeth; to leaue the vncertain, as <hi>Nicodemus, Ioſeph</hi> of Arimathia, <hi>Gamaleel, &amp;c,</hi> Before any ſacrament receiued: <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 19.9.</note> of <hi>Zacheus</hi> it is ſayd, <hi>This day is ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on come into thy houſe, O Zache:</hi> this day, not the day of his baptiſme: ſo the <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>Eunuch</hi> accepted to God by faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his baptiſme: ſo <hi>Cornelius</hi> a man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4474:19"/>
that feared God before his baptiſme: ſo <hi>Lydias</hi> hart opened, by the Lord,<note place="margin">Act. 10.2.</note> by the key of the word,<note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> as it were turned about by the preaching of it before baptiſme: ſo the iaylour in the ſame place: ſo <hi>Mary Magdelene</hi> that was caried to ſinne as if 7. diuels draue the tide, with wind and ſaile:<note place="margin">Luk. 17.50.</note> 
               <hi>Her faith ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her,</hi> as Chriſt ſayth, not her bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, vnles you ſay ſhee baptized her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with her teares: which though they were holy and precious water, fit to be preſerued in Gods bottle,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 56.8.</note> falling from her humbled cheekes, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart which God wiped with his mercie: which had many ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, becauſe ſhee loued much: yet they are not this actuall baptiſme of water which wee ſpeake of. So ſayth <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Aſella,</hi> ſanctified from the wombe.</p>
            <p>And in deede the very vſe of the Sacramentes which wee giue and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde the elect onely as wee hope, proueth a non neceſsitie of ſaluation in them and by them. For why are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4474:20"/>
children baptized,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.11.14.</note> becauſe they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though onely one parent ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: howe holy? and who holy? how holy, <note n="*" place="margin">Quaeſt. 3 de bapt. neceſſ.</note> not as the Ieſuits imagine holy, that is legitimate, no baſtarde: but holy, becauſe of the glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe of the couenant of grace:<note place="margin">Gen. 17 7. Act 2.39.</note> 
               <hi>I will be thy GOD and the God of thy ſeede.</hi> Who holy? only the baptized children of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: no, it is generally and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ſayd your children: as likewiſe of the whole Iewiſh race it is ſpoken, the roote being holy,<note place="margin">Rom 11.16.</note> ſo are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And why are the growen and them of diſcretion baptized? is it not that wee ſee ſome reaſon to ſeale vnto them Gods mercie? for baptiſme is a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e as was circumciſion.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> Now as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men the conditions are agreed vpon, then the ſeale annexed: ſo God receiueth into couenant, and then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. Men poſſeſſe their cattel and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and then marke them: they chuſe and leuie ſouldiers, &amp; then giue them preſt money: And yet as with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4474:20"/>
a good landlord, the right of my tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ceaſeth not, hauing the promiſe of a faithfull man, though the father ſhould die, without ſealing vnto mee, ſeeing an honeſt ſonne commeth in place, who will be a ſeale vnto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers words: ſo though GOD the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould preuent vs of baptiſme, yet in that he hath promiſed a ſtate of life to me and mine in his ſonne hee will ſeale it to vs, for him hath the father <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> ſealed. An honeſt ſouldier will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his life in the battailes of the lord, though hee had not his preſt money. The clayme of the owner is good, though no actuall marke ſhould bee vpon his good. This is the marke of Gods children,<note place="margin">Beza confeſ. c. 4. ſ. 48. de bapt. infant. Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treus Bern. ſer. 66. in Cant. Au l. 1. de peccat. meritis. Pet Martyr. lo. com. claſ. 4. c. 8. ſect 7. Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius. de Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. pag. 68. tom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lorde knoweth who are his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe if children in the wombe as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> or before baptiſme, and in their infancie haue faith, as diuers think, or haue the ſpirit of God as others, ſeeing they are partes of the Church as woe all profeſſe, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body of Chriſt, as wee all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4474:21"/>
ſay, howe can they periſh? none can take his ſheepe, nay not the leaſt lambe of a day olde, Iohn 10.29. nay not yet eaned nor brought into the world, out of his hande, though Sathan ſhould ſtande by to deuoure it vpon the verie birth,<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.4.5.</note> as he did once, for the child the verie ſonne of God, which was taken vp to Gods throne. And why may it not be, that as in earthly paradiſe, ſo in the heauenly Church?<note place="margin">Gen. 1.11.12.</note> As there are ſome trees and hearbes ſeeding, ſome budding, ſome bearing fruite: ſo in the heauenly paradiſe on earth, the Church, ſome of Gods ſeruants in the wombe, ſome budding out, ſome new waſht, as it were from the pooles. If the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> could bring an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting taint vpon them, ſhal not the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and death of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> wipe it out? The infant cannot reaſon, yet it hath the ſeed of reaſon, as it hath a ſoule, though it know not ſo much of it ſelfe. Thus ſome argue: May it not haue faith ſhed in the heart of it?<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.17.</note> for who can tell how God dwelleth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4474:21"/>
in the heart of the elect?<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> He that hath not the ſpirit of God, is none of his. Is not this the glorious impreſsion and ſtampe of that heauenly ſeale, that the child is aſſumpted into the aſſociation and fellowſhip of the bleſſed Trinitie,<note place="margin">Matth. 28.19.</note> into whoſe name it is baptized? Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt come to Chriſt.<note place="margin">Mark. 10.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: or as Luk. 18.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> What chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Little ones: they that are come to little reaſon, but that they abuſe in trifling, yet theirs is the kingdome of God. If theirs be the kingdom of God, then are they cleane:<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.27.</note> for no vncleane thing maye come in his pure ſight. Now what maketh cleane, but faith and Gods ſpirite? their hearts being purified alike by faith.<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> The working of Gods ſpirite, is like the inſenſible pearcing of the winde,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.8.</note> which getteth in no man knoweth how. And may it not get in into the hearts of little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? if their children bee holie, who can ſanctifie them, but the ſanctifier?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6 11.</note> why may not Gods ſpirite his winde get into them? and if they bee ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, then not damned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4474:22"/>Wherefore theſe ſpeeches of the childe vnbaptized: It is an heathen, an infidell, it is damned, I would not haue my child in the like caſe, for millions: are ſpeeches indeede heatheniſh, full of infidelitie, of raſh iudgement, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitablenes; not onely by damnato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſpeeches againſt the dead: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the liuing God, that hath taken them away as he would. Doth not the ſpirit ſpeake better things?<note place="margin">Luk. 6.37.</note> 
               <hi>Iudge not, and thou ſhalt not be iudged: condemne not, and thou ſhalt not be condemned:</hi> nay acquite, aſſoyle, deliuer, and thou ſhalt haue a meaſure of ſuch mercifull conſtruction meaſured vnto thee: not as thou vſeſt to doe, ſparingly, ſtreight by the brimmes of the meaſure: but with a meaſure preſſed downe, ſhaken together, and running ouer. And yet Proteſtants ſpeake ſo. So naturall a thing is Poperie, ſo quickly doe wee drinke in error before wee bee taught it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.20.</note>Haue we ſo learned Chriſt? are his lawes ſo ful of ruefulnes? Of <hi>Draco</hi> the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4474:22"/>
lawgiuer it is written, that al his lawes were death: death if thou doe this, death if thou doe not that, ſtill the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall noyſe of death ended the lawe. Therefore they note the pen to drop crueltie, the inke and writing to bee bloud. But Chriſt is no <hi>Draco,</hi> a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> He is a lambe that takes away the ſinnes of the whole world, a world of ſinnes: much more this lambe of God to heale theſe little la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes of his flocke. His lawes are not lawes of <hi>Draco,</hi> they ſpeake peace:<note place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> his bloud crieth better things then the bloud of <hi>Abel:</hi> for that crieth vengeance vpon <hi>Cayne</hi> his brother.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note> But Chriſts bloud crieth with a ſtrong voyce as of a mightie Angel: my bloud for all bloud:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> my bodie for all ſinne, euen of mine enemies. This were to make Chriſt an <hi>Herode:</hi> for <hi>Herode</hi> ſent out his men of warre to ſley and murder moſt butcherly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants from two yeares old downward,<note place="margin">Matth 2.16.</note> among whom were ſome vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: then <hi>Rachel</hi> in Rama lifts vp bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter voyces of lamentation; no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4474:23"/>
they are not. Indeede if Chriſt were not a Herauld of peace rather, then a <hi>Herod,</hi> and that hee ſent out his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of warre, as death and graue to deuoure, the diuell and hell to damne the vnbaptized: then indeede might <hi>Rachel</hi> lift vp her voyce, &amp; put on her mourning weede: then euery mother and father, ſiſter and brother, might howle and weepe, and anſwere one an other with dolefull ecchoes and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles complaints, no comfort, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, becauſe they are not: nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are, that is, they are in endles ſorowe: for better it were not to bee at all. But bleſſed bee God who hath ſealed a better couenant:<note place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> With thee and thy ſeede I make my couenant: bleſſed bee God who hath cleared our comfort:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.11.14 Eſay. 9.6.</note> Your children are holy: Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God that concerning the childe borne in <hi>Eſai,</hi> hath cauſed heauen and earth to heare a better melodie from an armie of heauenly ſouldiers:<note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Glorie to God on high, peace on earth belowe, good will towards men.</hi> Doe I ſpeake
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4474:23"/>
this alone? doe not likewiſe the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall voyce and language of Canaan,<note place="margin">Nehe. 13.24. Eſay. 19.18.</note> I meane the Iſrael of God, ſpeake ſo?</p>
            <p>Doth our Church alone thinke ſo? and doth not other Churches make vp the harmonie?<note place="margin">Rogers in the Engliſh Creed ſet out by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, pag. 33. par. 2 art. 25</note> The Creede of our Church confeſſeth this among the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Papiſts: that ſo many as are not incorporated into the viſible Church, by the Sacraments, at the leaſt of Baptiſme, are aſſuredly damned: So doth two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſsions of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> the confeſsion of the Church of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> the Proteſtant Church of <hi>France,</hi> ſo of <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſo of <hi>Auſpurge,</hi> ſo of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and <hi>Sweueland,</hi> which may be ſeene more at large in the booke of the Harmonie of confeſsions. <hi>Alanus Cope</hi> reckoneth this vp as one of our errors in <hi>England:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dial 6. cap. 9.</note> Infants before they are baptized, to belong to the people of GOD And to this agreeth moſt ſoundly euen he which hath now, by the diſpoſition of God, the chief place in this Church,<note place="margin">In his replie in the great vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume pag. 516.</note> and profeſſeth that he miſliketh the opinion of theſe, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4474:24"/>
thinke out of Ioh. 3. infants to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, being not baptized as much as any. It ſhall bee ambition to muſter the names of them who haue borne the ſtandard in their places, and are on our ſide: ſo doth <note n="*" place="margin">Aret. proble. theol. par. 2 de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſacr.</note> 
               <hi>Aretius</hi> at Barnes, <note n="*" place="margin">Caluin inſtit. l. 4. c. 16. ſec. 26.</note>
               <hi>Caluin</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Confeſſ. c. 4. ſect. 49. Zuingl. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Dei. c. 6. tom. 1. pa. 369.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> at Geneua: certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Zuinglius</hi> at Zurich, calleth them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentaries who attribute ſo much grace to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo much vertue to Baptiſme of it ſelfe. Such a cloud of witneſſes hath this trueth, and this is not only the conſent of the later Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but euen a long hath teſtimonie from this Apoſtle, Baptiſme ſaueth, but I meane not ſayeth hee, the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the water, but the examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a good conſcience towardes God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.26.</note>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt gaue himſelfe for the Church to ſanctifie it by the lauer of water:</hi> but how? through the word.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 8.2.</note> In <hi>Dauids</hi> time the Church profeſſeth GODS praiſe, out of the mouth of ſucklings: In the primitiue Church the Cathecumen the not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4474:24"/>
not onely ſaued, but glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Martyrs: ſuch an one was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclides Origens</hi> ſcholler, beheaded vnder <hi>Seuerus:</hi> and <hi>Rhais</hi> a woman, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, to haue obtained Baptiſme by fire.<note place="margin">Cyp epiſt. ad lubia.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> about the 260. yeare after Chriſt, profeſſeth that not only ſuffering for Chriſt,<note place="margin">De conſe. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinc. 4. ca. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi.</note> but faith and conuerſion of the heart ſupplieth the want of Baptiſme. The councell of <hi>Nice</hi> ſayth, our Baptiſme is not to bee conſidered with ſenſible eyes, but with the eyes of the mind.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Ora. ſunes. de obitu Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> about 380. yeare after Chriſt ſayth of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperour, who dyed without Baptiſme: Chriſt baptized him when mens offices failed: againe, his faith waſhed him. Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in l. de ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ad Petrum.</note> though he is alone almoſt except them that ſuruiued in his owne age in the neceſsitie of Sacraments, making out of the ſixt of <hi>Iohn</hi> a neceſsitie of the ſupper euen for infants:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.53.</note> becauſe it is ſayd, <hi>Vnleſse you eate the fleſhe of the Sonne of man and drinke his bloud, you haue no life in you:</hi> contrary to the rule
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4474:25"/>
of the Apoſtle, that none ſhould eate but they who can examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.</note> yet in diuers places where God asſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him more, and hee remembred himſelfe,<note place="margin">Aug. l. 13. de ciuit. Dei. ca 7.</note> he yeelded alſo to this truth, making faith and a contrite ſpirit to be in ſtead of Baptiſme, for thus hee ſaith, he that ſayd: <hi>Vnles a man be borne of water and the ſpirite hee cannot enter into the kingdome of God,</hi> Ioh. 3. ſayd as generally: <hi>Hee that confeſſeth mee before men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.8.</note> 
               <hi>I will confeſſe him before my Father and the holy Angels:</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that leeſeth his life, ſhall ſaue it:</hi> and againe, Pſal. 116.15. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious is the death of the Saints in the ſight of God.</hi> Nay hee rather commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them that dye ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Baptiſme, for others for feare of death defer not their baptiſme further: but theſe for loue to God deferre to liue longer, he exemplifieth alſo in the theefe: and <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. lib. 4. de baptiſ. in don. cap. 24.</note> againe, then is Baptiſme fulfilled, when not the contempt of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but when the inſtant or mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of neceſsitie excludeth from viſible
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4474:25"/>
Baptiſme. <note n="*" place="margin">Serm ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes.</note> Againe, none is depriued of the benefit of the ſacrament, ſo long as hee findeth in himſelfe the thing which the ſacrament ſignifieth: again, among whom do you reckon children vnbaptized? verely among beleeuers.<note place="margin">Aug de verbis Apoſtoli. ſer. 14.</note> 
               <hi>So. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de quaeſt. vet. teſt.</hi> The inuiſible ſanctification may bee without the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſigne, as the viſible ſigne without the true ſanctification.<note n="*" place="margin">In ſerm. de 40. Martyribus</note> 
               <hi>Baſile</hi> ſayth of the iaylour or keeper of the 40. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, who became a Martyr: hee was baptized by his owne faith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not by the hand of another: not in water, but in his owne blood. <hi>Hieromes</hi> iudgement of <hi>Aſella</hi> we heard aboue.</p>
            <p>Yet the diuerſitie of cuſtomes and practiſe of olde is ſtrange herein with the multitude of humane inuentions crept in euen in the primitiue church, that wee may bleſſe God for this puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Baptiſme which we enioy.<note place="margin">De conſecr. diſt 4. cap. non ratione &amp; in ſeq Terrul de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ dutiuſculè loquitur.</note> For they vſed only ſolemne times for bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, as Eaſter at Rome, by Victors conſtitution, at Eaſter and Pentecoſt in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time: or the time of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4474:26"/>
mariage, or at their dying day, or on the feaſt of the Epiphany, as in Aſia inſomuch that as Chriſt at 30. yeares of age was baptized:<note place="margin">Baptiſme more ſyncere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed now then of olde.</note> ſo <hi>Gregorie</hi> at 30. yeares olde, though his father were a Biſhop. So <hi>Austen</hi> about the ſame time, ſo <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a Biſhop elect before hee was baptized, and in a Synode of Rome 40 yeares are appointed, except for the ſicke,<note place="margin">In 4. Orat. de. Lauac. ſanct.</note> and great with childe, who might at all other times bee bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized And <hi>Nazianzene</hi> appointed the 4. yeare, when they could giue a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their faith: ſo that when a man once departeth from this, that any thing ſaueth, ſpeedy Baptiſme, or Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme deferred: Baptiſme or no Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, nay prayer or no prayer, word or no word, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing ſaueth, but this onely Sauiour Chriſt, who roſe, aſcended, raigneth ouer men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, one error increaſeth vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one inuention accrueth vpon his former: hence came the croſſe:<note n="*" place="margin">Origen. ho. 2. in Pſal. 38. Tertul. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. Cyp. de haer. bapt.</note> hence a kiſſe in Baptiſme, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 8. <hi>Cyp.</hi> hence a ring. <hi>Tertul. l. de pudicitia.</hi> hence to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4474:26"/>
haue oyle, <note n="*" place="margin">Tertul. de Cor. mil. &amp; l. x. contr. Mar. Hiero. ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer.</note> and milke, and hony in Baptiſme, not to waſh all the weake after Baptiſme: as nyce men waſh not after the trimming a while from the barber. Euen <hi>Constantine</hi> the good Emperour ſuperſtitiouſly deſired to be baptized in Iordan, as <hi>Naaman</hi> would carie ſome earth from thence (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſhould haue caried water rather,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> but that ſuperſtition is fooliſh) which yet <hi>Constantine</hi> obtained not, but was baptized at Nicomedia feared by death to deferre it further. Hence it came that they deferred Baptiſme till death, that al ſins might be forgiuen at once, and grewe to baptizing by <note n="*" place="margin">De conſec. diſt. 4. ca con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat. &amp; in ſeq.</note> lay people, &amp; women, &amp; ſometime to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue Baptiſme with ſand: and yet the ſtory of a Iew Baptized with ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Niceph. l. 3. c. 37.</note> who after had water added to him auow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their feare to depart from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
            <p>So good a thing is it to ſticke to the pure &amp; vnmedled beginning of word and ſacraments, to looke to the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and cleere fountaines. God ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4474:27"/>
it pure and in ſimplicitie, without mixture of additaments,<note place="margin">Eccle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31.</note> but men fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out many inuentions, as the ſcripture ſpeaketh in another caſe, howe good then is it to giue that vnto God which is due vnto God, that vnto the creature which is due vnto it, that vnto Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme which appertaineth vnto it? The Synod of Neocaeſaraea noteth theſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors by the conſent of 17. Biſhops: he that is baptized in ſickneſſe not to bee admitted to the office of any <note n="*" place="margin">Ad Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. Euſeb. l. 6 c. 43</note> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in the Church. <note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. 77. ad Hugo.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> in a long Epiſtle, proueth in his time that this trueth continued vntill his time, prouing that not the abſence but contempt of Baptiſme condemneth. And this is not onely the voyce in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Babilon heard of it, &amp; the ſtrength of the truth hath made diuers of them to yeelde, and hath prouoked one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another.<note place="margin">Tho. Par. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 art. 3.</note> Their <hi>Thomas</hi> who ſayde more for Popery then them all, though as pitch hee defile holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and many other holy thinges wherewith he medled: yet ſayth hee,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4474:27"/>
a man expecting the ſet time of the Church for Baptiſme, though he bee preuented by death, he is ſaued. <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> (Reader of Rome)<note place="margin">Quaeſt. de Baptiſ.</note> in his Dictates is greatly troubled not with anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs, but with <hi>Caietane,</hi> the flowre of their Cardinals, with <hi>Gerſon</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Paris,</hi> with <hi>Titleman</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Papiſt: that as Chriſt wroong out teſtimonie from Sathan, ſo hath the trueth in this poynt ſet falſehood vpon the racke, and made it confeſſe.</p>
            <p>Nay, theſe Papiſts being vrged but by their owne conſideration of the matter, they leaue a ſound teſtimonie. So doth <hi>Biell</hi> a great ſchooleman: So doth <hi>Alzimoney</hi> diſcourſe,<note place="margin">Tract. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ.</note> a diligent &amp; learned writer on their ſide, ſaying: Neceſſary is two-fold, either abſolute, as meate for life, or as conuenient, and fit to atchieue our purpoſe, as the horſe for the end of our iourney. Baptiſme is neceſſarie this laſt way. So that the aduerſarie giues iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t on our ſide: ſo great a conſent hath this truth: ſuch a peale of voyces God hath raiſed to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4474:28"/>
repeale the bloudie Herodian decree of Rome: ſo ſtrong a crye of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches neere and farre off, at home and abroade, of later and more ancient, of Scriptures, Councels and Fathers, friends and enemies, crying out vpon them that menace hell and death and wrath to the babes vnwaſhed, who meaſure ſo hard a meaſure to poore infants, as becauſe they enioy little of this life, they muſt leeſe al the next life, not heauen, but a hell, no honour of buriall, but to bee buried ſeparatly, as though they ſhould infect the reſt.</p>
            <p>And yet ſee pitifull hearts in the middeſt of crueltie ſome drop of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note place="margin">Limbus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantum.</note> an eaſie hell, a brimme of hell, not ſo bad as the damned is the hell for theſe forlorne innocents, a hell not ſo bad as for the actuall ſinners. Who ſayth ſo?<note place="margin">Bellar de purg. lib. 2. ca. 6. col. 790. A. in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olum.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine, Florence</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 3. the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: but no more: and theſe be their proofes: As if one ſhould ſay, a corrupt vpſtart Iudge, his court, bench, and a packe of falſe Notaries: but none of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4474:28"/>
them hauing any gray haire of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitic. This admiration of the effect of Baptiſme, and thus to be enamored vpon the element, made the heretikes <hi>Marcion</hi> and his,<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. 1. &amp; 4. in Marcion. Philaſtr.</note> and the <hi>Cataphry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> and theirs, to baptize euen the dead: euen as the Papiſts baptize euen bels, and that not by meane Miniſters, but euen by Biſhops. O fooliſh &amp; mad generation: But haue they no reaſon for it?</p>
            <p>Yes, they make a ſhewe of miracle, of Scripture, of Fathers. That they may ſeeme to bee mad with reaſon, Scripture, Fathers, miracles: Miracles out of <hi>Euodius:</hi> Scriptures eſpecially 2: <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. Fathers among the ancient, eſpecially <hi>Austin.</hi> I my ſelfe haue in this argument alleadged Fathers, contrarie to my ordinary vſe, ſeeing indeed Gods voyce alone ſhuld bee heard.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10 13.</note> But to let you ſee the line of expoſition, that I goe not alone in a ſingularitie, but haue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the Paſtors of other ages and Churches. <hi>Alanus Cope</hi> telleth a fabulous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4474:29"/>
to prooue it: A woman whoſe ſonne dyed vnbaptized, brings him dead before the memorie of S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> moaning that ſhe had loſt her child in this life and in the life to come: Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly life enters into him, a Prieſt is ſent for, the childe was baptized, and preſently dyed againe. O ſpirite of witchery which maketh them to truſt lying fables: for firſt of al himſelfe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth fall ſomewhat that ſtaineth his witneſſe: he ſaith in <hi>Auſtins</hi> ſermons of late imprinted at <hi>Iouaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The booke not written by Eudius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut to him.</note> two clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to too vnindifferent to condemne millions of infants: The miracle a night witneſſe:<note place="margin">Alanus Copus Dal. 3. cap 25.</note> the teſtimonie vpſtart. Why of late printed? Why at <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaine?</hi> Secondly, herein they bewray that the voyce of God hath nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe babes: ſeeing as Chriſt ſayd to the woman, when none durſt condemne her, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. <hi>Neither doe I condemne thee:</hi> So when Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes them not, that they muſt ſet teſtimonies from vauts &amp; ſepulchers, and from the withered bones of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4474:29"/>
dead men. But yet theſe little ones, their bones are not bruſed:<note place="margin">Mark. 10.14.</note> theirs alſo is the kingdome of God. For thirdly, why did not the mother carrie it to his owne graue, and not to S. <hi>Steuens</hi> tombe? or rather, why did ſhe at all bring a damned carkaſſe within hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ground, againſt their cuſtome? and good reaſon if for euer, it be Gods enemie, a damned miſcreant, why ſhould it haue the honour of buriall? Fourthly, if it were damned before, &amp; the ſoule gone to hell: is there redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from hell, againſt all trueth, and their owne iudgement? Fiftly, why preſently a Prieſt ſent for? might ſhe not thinke the ſame power that reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red life to her childe, able to preſerue him in life? or was not the life quite gone at al, and this deuiſe taken vp by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact to nouriſh ſuperſtitious minds, or if it muſt needes bee preſently bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, becauſe this their falſe Saint <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> gaue it ſuch a weake deadly life, that would not hold out, why might not her ſelfe, or ſome woman preſent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4474:30"/>
(for it is not improbable others alſo to haue gone with her in neighborhood or ſuperſtition) according to their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, haue baptized it: but they muſt tarie the time till a Prieſt come, who hold in their good diuinitie in ſuch a caſe of neceſsitie, that euen women may doe it: or laſtly, why did ſhe not goe to Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> for a ſecond life?</p>
            <p>But lyers and inuentors haue no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute good memories: let vs come to their ſcriptures, they are two: the firſt, Ioh. 3 5. <hi>Except a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be borne of water &amp; the ſpirit, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nnot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi> This place neceſſarily infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſay they, the neceſsity of baptiſme. Why? the words; are plaine, and yet if ſo, it is as plaine for them that vſe a hot <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Iron in Baptiſme, not to go from this matter, for example, becauſe it is ſayd, <hi>Chriſt ſhall baptize with the holy Ghoſt &amp; with fire:</hi> and not to goe from this place, it is as plaine for an olde man to be borne againe: ſo plaine that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap>enus</hi> once miſtook it, though a maſter in Iſraell. But to come to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4474:30"/>
meaning: doth water ſignifie here of neceſsitie, the element of water vſed in Baptiſme: howe knowe they that? for in the former chapter no occaſion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is giuen to ſpeake of Baptiſme, nor in the beginning of this. And ſecondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt ſeemeth rather to tell what is neceſſary for men in yeares, who can make profeſsion as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> who diſſembled, then for infants: neither is any mention made of Baptiſme all the time of his abode in Galile, where he was at the marriage, or whilſt he was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> at Ieruſalem, where this ſpeech ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee vntill hee came into Iury, verſ. 22. As though Chriſt ſayd: thou wouldeſt learne the way to heauen, &amp; thou knoweſt it in part alreadie, that I am a teacher come from God, verſ. 1. And yet thou halteſt in the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two, and goeſt vpright in the night onely: but I tell thee, I being a true teacher tell thee that thou muſt walke as a child of the day, thou muſt be borne againe, that is, bee renued in the ſpirit of thy minde to bee of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4474:31"/>
iudgement, euen to profeſſe the name of God ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, els thou canſt not ſee the kingdome of God: Vnles thou <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſhewe thy ſelfe to be in my kingdome of the Goſpell by open profeſsion on earth, thou canſt not ſee my kingdome aboue:<note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> Except a man, that is, of ſuch a iudgement as thou alreadie art, and all naturall men be,<note place="margin">verſ. 4.</note> be borne againe and altered in the ſpirit, they cannot ſee the kingdome of God. When he maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led what it was to bee borne againe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Chriſt expoundeth it thus: <hi>I ſay, vnles he bee borne againe of water and the ſpirit:</hi> making it all one to be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of the ſpirit and of water: and the ſpirit, making it all one to be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of one of them and of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both: and which is the more excluſiue? for that which he had ſayd in one word, <hi>Except a man be borne of the ſpirit,</hi> he after expoundeth the manner how the ſpirit muſt work, as water in waſhing vs, in ſanctifying vs, in renuing vs. For he ſayth, <hi>Vnles a man be borne of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the ſpirit:</hi> which to bee the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4474:31"/>
meaning, the tenour and paſſage of all the ſpeech had with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, as firſt the oppoſing of earthlie birth, and ſpiritual, verſ 6. <hi>That which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> is borne of fleſh, is fleſh:</hi> which ſentence proueth rather, that water ſaueth not: as though fleſhly, earthly, and carnall things can goe no further then fleſh, earth, nor haue no further effects: A mans ſoule is a ſpirite: water an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie bodie: an earthly thing can not purge a ſpirituall ſubſtance: no proportion betweene the agent &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, the doer and ſufferer: euen as of old the bloud of beaſts could not take away ſinnes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.2.3. ſo not now the waſhing of water can take away ſinne. Secondly, the aſcribing of the meanes to Gods free-will, verſ. 8. and his loue, verſ. 16. by the worke of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſpirite, and incarnation of the ſonne, verſ. 13. telling the hardnes of it, verſ. 8.11.12. whereas outward waſhing is eaſie: finally, in that verſe 18. Chriſt maketh faith the meanes of ſaluation, and not faith damnation: <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4474:32"/>
is ſaued: he that beleeueth not is damned.</hi> So that vnles a man will ſay that infants haue faith, this toucheth infants nothing at all: and if they haue faith, then thoſe only ſaued, who haue this faith by the gift of God. So that this general rule, <hi>Except,</hi> proueth this: that without conuerſion of heart, and renuing of the ſpirit of our minde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, there is no ſaluation. And that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> by water is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Gods ſpirit; the fruits, the graces of it, many ſcriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, eſpecially in the ſtile and phraſe of Chriſt himſelfe in this Euangeliſt: in the next chapter, verſ. 14. <hi>He that drinketh of the water which I giue, ſhal neuer thirſt:</hi> for Baptiſme is not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a wel of water to euerlaſting life, therefore it is ment of Gods ſpirit: &amp; the miracle of Chriſt healing without water,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> declareth that the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ought not to be in that credite. So <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.39. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <hi>He that beleeueth, riuers of water of life ſhall flow out of his bellie.</hi> But if any man aske: how will you proue water to ſignifie the ſpirit here? I anſwere,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4474:32"/>
euen hence, verſ. 39. This he ſayd of the ſpirit: It alſo hath the accord of the old Teſtament, ſo <hi>Iere.</hi> 2.3.10. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 4.4. <hi>The Lorde ſhall waſh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the filthines of Sion, with the ſpirit of iudgement and burning.</hi> Laſtly, I aske whether if this propoſition, verſ. 5 bee generall excluſiue, <hi>Except a man be borne of water and the ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> why the former propoſition, verſ 3. which is firſt by nature, conſiſting of as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tearmes in arte: <hi>Except a man bee borne of the ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> be not as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: which if it bee, and what reaſon can be ſhewed to the contrarie, then it being alſo general and excluſiue, why ſhould it not ſhut out the neceſsitie of materiall water?</p>
            <p>Here alſo if abſolutely materiall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> water be vnderſtood, then no Martyr ſaued without it, not the theefe on the croſſe, not the Apoſtles vnbaptized, not the good Emperour <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and many other who in priſon, or warre deſire it. The other place, Mark. 16.16. anſwereth it ſelfe, aſcribing all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4474:33"/>
to faith, for hauing ſayd, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth and is baptized ſhall bee ſaued:</hi> addeth ſtraight way to preuent error, <hi>but he that beleeueth not,</hi> and not hee that is not baptized, <hi>ſhall bee damned.</hi> Now as for <hi>Austen,</hi> it is true that hee in the matter of the ſacraments neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, yea in both of them made it an exigence of neceſsitie, both to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: ſo that as vpon this place, he groundeth though falſly as vpon a foundation of water, the neceſsitie of Baptiſme, ſo vpon the next place, Ioh. 6.53. <hi>Vnles ye eate the fleſh of the Son of man, and drinke his blood, yee haue no life in you.</hi> Not only hee but <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentius</hi> &amp; al that age almoſt ground a neceſsitie of the Supper, inſomuch that they gaue it to infants contrary to the rule of <hi>Paul,</hi> Let a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> examine him ſelfe, &amp;c. &amp; the meaning of this place, which is of the ſpirituall receiuing of Chriſt and incorporating into him by the ſpirite in generall, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by the meanes of the ſpirite wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the worde, in Baptiſme, or in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4474:33"/>
the Supper, or in whatſoeuer. Fitly is it ſayd to this purpoſe by Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> in Pſalm. 147. When we heare the worde of the Lorde, the fleſh of Chriſt and his bloud is powred in at our eares.</p>
            <p>Let vs now come to the vſe,<note place="margin">The third and laſt part.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ende, and neceſsitie of Baptiſme: which though it be not abſolutely, &amp; ſimply neceſſarie, yet in his due place and time, if it may bee had according to Chriſts inſtitution, cannot bee neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, without great ſinne. For herein of diuers men there are diuers extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: as of the moſt of the Papiſts, who make it abſolutely neceſſarie: ſo of the Manichees on the other ſide, who generally cut off al ſignes,<note place="margin">Aug. in Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum. lib. 19.</note> becauſe they making God not to be the author of theſe ſenſible and earthly things, thereupon inferred, that the worſhip by theſe earthly things could not bee gratefull to him. So the Cathatiſts, who becauſe God is a ſpirit, and men muſt worſhip him in ſpirit, reiected all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4474:34"/>
helpe of earthly meanes. And laſt of all,<note place="margin">Aug. haer. 88.</note> the Pelagians who becauſe they exempt men from originall ſinne, doe thinke Baptiſme needles, to purge that which is not: wherein you may firſt ſee the notable, wilfull, and ſpitefull malice of the Rhemiſts, who in <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5. ioyne the Caluiniſts and Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans together, as both promiſing alike life eternall to children dying without Baptiſme: when as they differ as hell and heauen in the cauſes of ſaluation. For <hi>Caluin</hi> acknowledgeth children to bee vnder originall ſinne: <hi>Pelagius</hi> did not: yet <hi>Caluin</hi> thinketh not the elect of God to periſh, if in ſome caſe they bee preuented of outward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Laſtly of Anabaptiſts, who would not haue infants baptized, but them of yeares: againſt whom at this time, beſide that which is ſayd aboue, this may be ſufficient: that ſeeing chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſin, they ought to be waſhed: and ſeeing they belong vnto GOD, they ought to bee ſealed. As for the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4474:34"/>
Manichees, ſeeing wee acknowledge the ſame Lord Creator of heauen and earth, one God maker of both, the ſame almightie and moſt holie ſpirite to haue made the greateſt Angell and moſt deſpiſed worme: and that hee made al things good, and to a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent end, that therefore both againſt them and the Cathariſts,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> though it be true that bodily exerciſe profiteth lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; as waſhing by water, taking of bread and wine, much reading, much repeating of prayer, much hearing and ſitting by it to heare, much preaching alſo, vnles the ſpirit alſo concurre and our inwarde deſire: yet as God made bodie and ſpirit, and therefore muſt be glorified in both: ſo ſeeing he made both viſible and inuiſible things, both ſpirituall and corporall things, both ſerue for his glorie, both are helpers of our faith; if firſt wee remember, that we vſe them, when wee haue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word of God for them. As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lorde biddeth vs baptize
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4474:35"/>
with water: therefore in doing ſo we build vpon the rocke: and we thinke wee ſhould tempt GOD, if when he ſhould teach vs the waſhing away of our ſinnes in Chriſt, by the powring on of water, wee ſhould refuſe ſuch a comfortable and liuely repreſentation, and deſerue to heare the check that K. <hi>Achaz</hi> had, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 7.11.12. who being in weakneſſe of faith when Ieruſalem was beſieged, would not aske a ſigne, when the offer was made in Chriſt, but was reproued as one not that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the miniſter and bringer of the ſigne, but had grieued the God of the miniſter, and author of that ſigne. <hi>Is it a ſmall thing to grieue men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>but you muſt alſo grieue my God?</hi> ſayth <hi>Eſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The defeating of Baptiſme ſeemeth to come three waies: one by open contempt and deſpiſing of Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in it: Heatheniſh and prophane men cannot tell what to make of the ſprinkling of water, nor of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it in the name of the bleſſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4474:35"/>
as the Infidels, and Atheiſts, and Paynims doe vnto this day, being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that Chriſt <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. when he ordained Baptiſme, ſayd: Al power in heauen and earth is giuen vnto me, goe and baptize, I am with you for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: So that here is not naked water, or the bare cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or a few words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated: but here is the power of God with it, his wiſedome to eſtabliſh it, his conſtancie to auowe it, his holines to ſanctifie it, his mercie to bleſſe it: ſo that as an odde thing, or new thing they which deſpiſe it, deſpiſe not ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aduiſe, but Gods counſel againſt them ſelues, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.30. as did the Phariſies. And hee that will not followe Gods counſell, how ſhall he thriue, though all the heads in the world ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe for him? Another diſappoyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Baptiſme commeth by negligence, as in the people of Iſrael intermitting circumciſion for 40. yeares,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.24.</note> as in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who no doubt acknowledged Gods ordinance for circumciſion, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4474:36"/>
yet either hauing learned Aegyptian or Midianitiſh manners, or to pleaſe his wife, deferred to do it, ſo that God had like to deſtroyed him in the Inne for it. Which I would haue parents conſider, that defer their childrens baptiſme from Lords day to Lords day, and from one time of aſſemblie to another, for no end but to get ſuch and ſuch witneſſes, ſuch and ſuch furniture of their houſes, and ſuch other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, and outward circumſtances, till death ſtrike their children: which ſinne though the Lord may remit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet their comfort cannot be ſo great, as if they had taken the due time which the Lord offered them: ſeeing by their meanes it commeth to paſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and place and time and all did concurre, they only were wanting, by the ſinne of omiſsion: which thing gouernours Eccleſiaſtical are to looke vnto, leſt that if euery man by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſhould defer if death ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept, Anabaptiſtrie might creepe in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4474:36"/>
and ſcarſe any child be baptized. The Primitiue Church ſuffered them to want an honourable buriall,<note place="margin">Concil. 1. Braccar.</note> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their baptiſme. Of the third de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>featement of Baptiſme, by vnauoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable neceſsitie, wee haue ſpoken at large, when either the child is preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by death in the wombe, or out of the wombe: either by negligence or contempt in parents and friends, as in theſe two laſt caſes: or when parents and miniſter, and all are willing, death creepeth in and preuenteth both.</p>
            <p>Such occurrents may bee matter of meditation to parents, and Miniſters, and the whole people, of the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death, of the vncertaine ioy and ſtay of poſteritie, that he ſuffereth vs to beget, but not to poſſeſſe; to haue a ſight of our babes, and then ſuddenly taketh them to himſelfe; of Gods al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightines, that he doth what he will, and that ſometimes hee ſaueth with meanes, ſometimes without meanes, as ſometimes damneth with meanes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4474:37"/>
ſometimes without meanes: but yet not ſo that any of theſe accidents o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the election of God. What then eſtabliſheth the ſubſtance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? what ouerthroweth it? Here wee muſt conſider the inſtitution: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>Goe:</hi> Who? The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: Do what? <hi>baptize,</hi> that is, powre on the water, or dippe it in water: Whom? <hi>all nations,</hi> that is men, not bels, &amp;c. How? not in the name of the water, or power of it, or any other name in heauen or earth: but of the bleſſed Trinitie. So that a Midwife to baptize, or a priuate man, to whom it was neuer ſayd, <hi>Goe, and baptize:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to vſe ſande, as ſometime hath bin, or ſome other licour: <note n="*" place="margin">As oyle and water, by Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. ib. 1. cap. 18.</note> alſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie it to bels, &amp; then forſooth Biſhops alone muſt do it, as the Papiſts vſe: and laſtly not to doe it in the name &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and vertue of the Trinitie, I take it to bee the violating of the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: in which kinds wee ought to refuſe it. But if other circumſtances
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4474:37"/>
onely be annexed or not accompanie it,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.31.</note> as it may be truly ſayd of this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: (God made it ſimple and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and vncompounde, but man founde out many inuentions) theſe things may a little exerciſe our zeale and faith and patience: but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abridge the counſel of God in thee and thine: and therefore if thou maiſt haue it without the additamentes of men, the better it is: if not, yet the ſeale of God remaineth ſure, they ſhall beare their iniquitie of ſtubble, ſo meane a matter built vpon ſo good a foundation that haue brought it vp, or maintaine it: vntil God purge them by his triall of fire, as in the worde, ſo in the ſacrament, <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.15.</note> when as the ſtubble ſhall vaniſh, but the good foundation ſhall ſaue them. Doe thou as much as thou canſt communicate with God in his inſtitution: for as we are to deſire not onely the milke of the worde,<note place="margin">1. Peter 2.2.</note> but the ſyncere milke of it: ſo in the Lords ſeale, wee ought rather to take his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4474:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:4474:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:4474:39"/>
alone then any characters of man.</p>
            <p>And to drawe to an ende, I would not onely haue men peremptorie for the Sacrament, but for the word alſo, which is the life of the Sacrament: what is water without the worde, but water? therefore if the neglect or the contempt of the Sacrament bee a ſinne, is not the deſpiſing of the word, and neglect of it a ſinne alſo? becauſe many are wonderfull paſsionate,<note place="margin">The neceſſitie of the word to be thought on, as of Baptiſme</note> if God himſelfe preuent of Baptiſme, but themſelues for themſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are nothing compaſsionate: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no care nor conſcience of their aſsiduitie and diligence to heare the word. Surely the worde hath ſaued without Baptiſme, but baptiſme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the worde neuer: Ioh. 15.3. <hi>You are cleane becauſe of the word:</hi> and that you may knowe the words deſpiſing hath power to damne alſo, conſider what the ſcripture ſaith, Ioh. 12.48. <hi>The word ſhall iudge you:</hi> and againe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4474:39"/>
               <hi>Hee that deſpiſeth the worde his prayer is abominable:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28.9.</note> and againe,<note place="margin">Math. 10.40.</note> 
               <hi>He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth the Preacher, reiecteth him that ſent him,</hi> which is the Lord: and againe, <hi>Faith commeth by hearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14. Rom. 14.23.</note> which faith alone pleaſeth GOD. Chriſt Math. 23.16. calles the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees <hi>blind guides, fooles and blind:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they counted it ſinne to ſweare by the gold of the Temple, but by the Temple to ſweare was nothing: ſo to ſweare by the Aultar, nothing, but by the offering vpon the Aultar a ſinne. Now fooles and blind, which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, gold or Temple, Altar or offering? For the Temple conteineth God that dwelleth in it: the Altar, that is God worſhipped at it. So let the deſpiſers of the word either vaniſh &amp; wonder, Act. 13.31. for Gods work vpon their blindnes that can ſee a mote of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in Baptiſme, and not the beame of contempt in the worde, or elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their blindnes: Baptiſme is as gold, it is as a holy offering: but
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4474:40"/>
yet the word ſanctifieth it, and if it be not offered as it were vpon the holy Altar of the word, this golde becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth droſſe, becauſe there wanteth Gods word, as fire to trie it: &amp; though it bee the offering of the fruite of thy body, thine owne fleſh to the Lorde, yet vnles thou doe it as the Lord hath commanded, there is a ſauour of death in it, and not of life: The propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion muſt be kept, Leuit. 17.4 In ſacrifices diſobedience is as murder: and why not in ſacraments?</p>
            <p>Wherefore beloued, let vs not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Baptiſme, let vs not deſpiſe the word: Baptiſme is good, and holy, and comfortable with the word, the word is wholſome, and comfortable in his place, with Baptiſme and without it, let vs get a ſpirite of diſcerning ſpirits, to diſtinguiſh betweene outward wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and inwarde, betweene the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of poperie, who ſowre the ſweete water of baptiſme &amp; make it Marah, let vs rather ſeaſon it with caſting in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4474:40"/>
ſome part of the tree of life,<note place="margin">2. King. 2.21.</note> as <hi>Eliza</hi> did to the waters of Iericho, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the land from vntimely birth. Let vs preſerue a good conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muning with our hearts dayly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo ſhal neither we, nor our church haue vntimely birth for ſaluation, as they had in Iericho: ſo ſhall not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme be vnfruitfull to vs, but be laden with all the benefites of Chriſts reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, aſcenſion, glorie at Gods right hand, and dominions ouer Angels, and then neither death nor life. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, nor not Baptiſme, neither things paſt, preſent, nor to come, ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Ieſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> which ſhal bring vs vnto God.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>In the epiſtle to the reader, page 4. line 27. for, inſancicida, reade infanticida. p. 45. l. 18. for, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, r. Seuenthly. p. 59. l. 17. for, that is God, r. God that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
